<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Building a mail server on Debian 6.0</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Goran</firstname>
      <surname>Jurić</surname></personname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2010</year>
      <holder>Goran Jurić</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <title>Legal Notices</title>

      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
      License (GFDL), Version 1.1 or any later version published
      by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections,
      no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  You can find
      a copy of the GFDL at this
      <link xl:href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/fdl.html">link</link>.
      </para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo>
      This is version 0.0.1 of Building a mail server on Debian.
    </releaseinfo>
  </info>

  <preface>
    <title>Foreword</title>

    <para>The internet is full of information on how to do just about
    anything. But this vast amount of information makes it hard to find and
    glue all of the pieces to fit together.</para>

    <para>The goal of this manual is to provide you with enough knowledge to
    feel confident in installing and maintaing your own mail server. Of course
    manuals like this already exist but during my search for knowledge I
    always felt like they were either not updated in a while or they just skip
    over some of the most interesting parts assuming you know what they are
    talking about.</para>

    <para>I will do my best to explain why and not just how.</para>

    <para>This manual does not even come close to explaining the intricacies
    of a Postfix mail server. If you want to know more you really should read
    "The Book of Postfix: State-of-the-Art Message Transport" by Ralf
    Hildebrandt and Patrick Koetter.</para>
  </preface>

  <xi:include href="chapters/Introduction.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Preparation.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/MailServer.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Security.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Todo.xml" />
</book>
