<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:ns2="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Building a mail server on Debian 6.0</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Goran</firstname>
      <surname>Jurić</surname></personname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2010</year>
      <holder>Goran Jurić</holder>
    </copyright>

    <releaseinfo>This is version 0.6.0 of Building a mail server on
    Debian.</releaseinfo>

    <revhistory>
    <revision>
      <revnumber>0.6.0</revnumber>
      <date>2011-03-14</date>
      <authorinitials>GJ</authorinitials>
      <revremark>Added a chapter on moving Amavisd-new configuration to MySQL</revremark>
    </revision>

    <revision>
      <revnumber>0.5.0</revnumber>
      <date>2011-02-21</date>
      <authorinitials>GJ</authorinitials>
      <revremark>Moved Bayes and AWL data info MySQL</revremark>
    </revision>

    </revhistory>


    <legalnotice>
      <title>Legal Notices</title>

      <para>This document is released under the
      Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported (CC BY-NC-SA 3.0)
      licence.</para>

      <para>You are free to Share (copy, distribute and transmit the work) and
      to Remix (to adapt the work) under the following conditions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>You must attribute the work in the manner specified by the
          author or licensor (but not in any way that suggests that they
          endorse you or your use of the work).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You may not use this work for commercial purposes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you alter, transform, or build upon this work, you may
          distribute the resulting work only under the same or similar license
          to this one.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Any of the above conditions can be waived if you get permission
      from the copyright holder. The full licence can be found <link
      ns2:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/legalcode">here</link>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </info>

  <preface xml:id="foreword">
    <title>Foreword</title>

    <para>The internet is full of information on how to do just about
    anything. But this vast amount of information makes it hard to find and
    glue all of the pieces to fit together.</para>

    <para>The goal of this manual is to provide you with enough knowledge to
    feel confident in installing and maintaing your own mail server. Of course
    manuals like this already exist but during my search for knowledge I
    always felt like they were either not updated in a while or they just skip
    over some of the most interesting parts assuming you know what they are
    talking about.</para>

    <para>I will do my best to explain why and not just how.</para>

    <para>This manual does not even come close to explaining the intricacies
    of a Postfix mail server. If you want to know more you really should read
    "The Book of Postfix: State-of-the-Art Message Transport" by Ralf
    Hildebrandt and Patrick Koetter.</para>
  </preface>

  <xi:include href="chapters/Introduction.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Preparation.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Security.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Postfix.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Courier.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Antispam.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Utilities.xml" />

  <xi:include href="chapters/Todo.xml" />

  <!--
  <xi:include href="chapters/MailServer.xml" />
-->
</book>
