<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="courier" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Courier</title>

  <para>For now, our server can receive emails, but we have no way of
  accessing those emails from a mail client. For this we are going to use
  <application>Courier</application> as our IMAP and POP server.</para>

  <para><application>Dovecot</application> is another popular option, but for
  this integration you will have to look elsewhere. For me, Dovecot is not an
  option because it does not automatically check for new mail in all of the
  IMAP folder when you select <option>Get Mail</option> option in your mail
  client. And since all of the emails marked as <emphasis>Spam</emphasis> is
  moved automatically to a <filename>Junk</filename> folder my client would
  not report to me if there are any new messages in the
  <filename>Junk</filename> folder unless I explicitly check for them.</para>

  <section xml:id="courier.installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <programlisting>apt-get install courier-authdaemon courier-authlib-mysql courier-pop courier-pop-ssl courier-imap courier-imap-ssl fam</programlisting>

    <para>If you do not want to use POP you can skip installing packages that
    provide POP and install only</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get install courier-authdaemon courier-authlib-mysql courier-imap courier-imap-ssl fam</programlisting>

    <para>When asked if you would like to create directories for web-based
    administration, answer <userinput>No</userinput>.</para>

    <para>Open <filename>/etc/courier/authdaemonrc</filename> and
    change</para>

    <screen>authmodulelist="authpam"</screen>

    <para>to</para>

    <screen>authmodulelist="authmysql"</screen>

    <para>Empty <filename>/etc/courier/authmysqlrc</filename> and paste the
    following (change you password).</para>

    <screen>MYSQL_SERVER localhost
MYSQL_USERNAME mailadmin
MYSQL_PASSWORD <userinput>newpassword</userinput>
MYSQL_PORT 0
MYSQL_DATABASE mail
MYSQL_USER_TABLE mailbox
MYSQL_CRYPT_PWFIELD password
MYSQL_UID_FIELD 5000
MYSQL_GID_FIELD 5000
MYSQL_LOGIN_FIELD username
MYSQL_HOME_FIELD "/home/vmail"
MYSQL_MAILDIR_FIELD CONCAT(SUBSTRING_INDEX(username,'@',-1),'/',SUBSTRING_INDEX(username,'@',1),'/')
MYSQL_QUOTA_FIELD concat(quota,'S')</screen>

    <para>Notice that the QUOTE_FIELD has an “S” appended to the value. This
    is because Postfix Admin stores MailDir quota as an integer, and Courier
    maildrop expects the quota value to be in the format XXXS, where XXX
    represent the number of bytes that can be stored in the Maildir, and “S”
    stands for size.</para>

    <para>Maildrop can also use XXXC, where “C” I guess stands for “COUNT”
    because this value stands for number of messages that MailDir can
    store.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="courier.certificates">
    <title>Use certificates</title>

    <para>Edit <filename>/etc/courier/imapd-ssl</filename> and change the
    values of <varname>TLS_CERTFILE</varname> and
    <filename>TLS_TRUSTCERTS</filename> to</para>

    <screen>TLS_CERTFILE=/etc/ssl/self-signed/server.pem
TLS_TRUSTCERTS=/etc/ssl/self-signed/server.crt</screen>

    <para>To restart Courier you have to restart couple of services.</para>

    <screen>/etc/init.d/courier-authdaemon restart
/etc/init.d/courier-imap restart
/etc/init.d/courier-imap-ssl restart</screen>

    <para>And if you have it installed POP3 you need to restart those as
    well.</para>

    <screen>/etc/init.d/courier-pop restart
/etc/init.d/courier-pop-ssl restart</screen>

    <para>If you would like users of every virtual domain on your server to
    connect to <systemitem
    class="fqdomainname">mail.their-domain.com</systemitem> instead of to
    <systemitem class="fqdomainname">atlantis.example.com</systemitem> you
    will have to sign new certificates for every domain and also use a
    separate IP address for each virtual host. Information on placing
    certificates for various hosts can be found in
    <filename>/etc/courier/imapd-ssl</filename>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="courier.firewall-rules">
    <title>Firewall rules</title>

    <para>You have to change Firewall rules to allow inbound connections to
    ports that Courier uses:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Pop and secure Pop use ports 110 and 995 respectively.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Imap and secure imap use ports 143 and 993 respectively.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="courier.commit-changes">
    <title>Commit your changes</title>

    <para>If you are using etckeeper now is a good time to commit the changes
    you made.</para>

    <programlisting>etckeeper commit "Configured Courier"</programlisting>
  </section>
</chapter>
