<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="introduction"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <section xml:id="introduction.why.postfix">
      <title>Why Postfix</title>
      
      <para>Most of you know that there are a number of different distributions and mail transfer
        agents that could be used to build an equally capable mail server.</para>

      <para>The only other mail server I had experience working on is build on CentOS and it is
        called <uri xlink:href="http://www.qmailtoaster.com/" xlink:type="simple">Qmail
        Toaster</uri>. Qmail Toaster has a lot of strengths. It is a ready made software
        library which you can install and the installer will take care of setting up a bunch
        of different programs and utilities that are needed for a mail server.</para>

      <para>On the other hand, from what I have seen, it has it's share of quirks and the biggest
        one for me is that it uses Qmail. Qmail is not a bad MTA (Mail Transfer Agent) but it
        is not being actively developed for years and a lot of the functionality is provided
        through patches.</para>

      <para>Postfix is on the other hand an actively developed project and all of the requirements
        a modern mail server could have are either present in Postfix itself or they can be
        provided through other applications.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="introduction.why.debian">
      <title>Why Debian</title>

      <para>Debian 3.0 (woody) is the first distribution I installed on a server and since than I
        fell in live with it. Debian was at the time the distribution with most packages provided
        in their repositories. Some of you maybe like to compile their own software, but for me
        software provided through distributions package management was always easier to maintain
        and upgrade and not to mention stable.</para>
        
      <para>CentOS is also a nice distribution, but the version of Postfix shipped with the current
        release of Centos (5.6 at the time of writing) is ancient and is not really even supported
        by the author. Not to mention that the number of software packages provided through the
        official repositories does not even come close to Debians.</para>
        
      <para>Software in the stable Debian distribution may be older than the one provided in Ubuntu
        distribution, but I have more trust in Debian. Your milage may vary.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="introduction.software-used">
      <title>Sofware used</title>

      <para>Here is a short list of application we are going to use to build a mail server.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Postfix - Mail Transfer Agent
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Courier - as an IMAP/POP3 server
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              SpamAssassin - for filtering spam messages
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              ClamAV - for checking email for viruses
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Amavisd-new - a glue that glues Postfix with SpamAssassin and ClamAV
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Sqlgrey - for greylisting emails
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              MySQL - for storing information about users, domains and settings
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              Maildrop - for delivering mails to users mailboxes
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="introduction.required-knowledge">
      <title>Required knowledge</title>
      
      <para>This is not a beginners guide to Unix. You should know your away around a unix
         shell and familiarize yourself with Debians package management <emphasis>apt</emphasis>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
