<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="preparation"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Preparation</title>

  <section xml:id="preparation.debian-installation">
    <title>Debian installation</title>

    <para>Download Debian 6.0 (32/64-bit PC Network installer) from <uri
    xlink:href="http://www.debian.org/" xlink:type="simple">
    www.debian.org</uri> and burn the image to a compact disc, or mount it as
    a CD image in your virtualisation software.</para>

    <para>Boot your computer and select Install (or Install 64 if you want the
    64-bit version). Choose your Language, Country and Keymap. If your
    computer is not connected to a network with <acronym>DHCP</acronym> you
    will be prompted to enter network connection parameter manually. After
    configuring your network and <acronym>DNS</acronym> server you will be
    asked for a hostname, in our case, the hostname is <systemitem
    class="systemname">atlantis</systemitem> and our domain name is
    <systemitem class="domainname">example.com </systemitem>.</para>

    <para>When prompted to select Debian mirror the selected choice is usually
    the best one. If you are not using <acronym>HTTP</acronym> proxy on your
    internet connection, or don't know what HTTP proxy is, just leave this
    field blank.</para>

    <para>When prompted to partition the disk for a Debian install, choose
    <computeroutput>Guided - use entire disk. Install all files in one
    partition</computeroutput>.</para>

    <para>Grab a cup of coffee and wait until installation finishes fetching
    packages from the internet and installs the base system.</para>

    <para>Enter your root password. This is a password for root user who has
    all the privileges on the system, so choose one carefully. After that, you
    have to create a new user for the system.</para>

    <para>You will be asked if you want to participate in the Debians
    popularity contest which collects information about most used packages.
    Feel free to answer whatever you like, by choosing Yes you are helping
    Debian community find the most used packages in the distribution. Help
    them out, it doesn't cost a thing.</para>

    <para>When prompted to select collections of software packages deselect
    everything, including the <computeroutput>Standard system
    utilities</computeroutput> We just need to install the base system because
    we will add all needed packages when and if we need them.</para>

    <para>I strongly believe that you should install the minimum required
    number of packages needed for the system to operate. You will not have to
    update and upgrade packages that you do not even use. And knowing which
    package provides certain utilities is a fun exercise in getting to know
    your system a little better.</para>

    <para>Since Debian will be the only system on our machine you must install
    GRUB on to the master boot record when prompted.</para>

    <para>Your Debian system is almost ready to go. When asked, remove the
    installation media from your drive (or unmount the image in your
    virtualisation software) and reboot your computer.</para>

    <para>When your computer boots up you can log in with the root user
    account and update the packages in your system by running:</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get update
apt-get upgrade</programlisting>

    <para>And that's it. Your new Debian system is installed and ready for
    configuration.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="preparation.tracking-changes">
    <title>Tracking configuration changes</title>

    <para>During the course of this manual, we will edit a lot of
    configuration files and install many application packages and sometimes it
    is really hard to remember what we did and why after a couple of months
    have passed.</para>

    <para>To stay on top of the game we will use
    <application>etckeeper</application>.</para>

    <para>Etckeeper is an application that uses version control systems like
    git, Bazaar or Mercurial to track changes made to the <filename
    class="directory">/etc</filename> folder.</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get install etckeeper</programlisting>

    <para>Etckeeper in Debian uses git for tracking changes and is set to
    automatically commit all of the changes before a new package is installed
    as well as to auto commit changes on a daily bases.</para>

    <para>Since i do now want to forget to describe changes I mage to the
    files in <filename class="directory">/etc</filename> I usaully disable
    automatic commits. Edit <filename>/etc/ectkeeper/etckeeper.conf</filename>
    and uncomment out these two lines:</para>

    <programlisting>AVOID_DAILY_AUTOCOMMITS=1
AVOID_COMMIT_BEFORE_INSTALL=1</programlisting>

    <para>Set name and email git will use for the commit log by running this
    two commands at the shell:</para>

    <programlisting>git config --global user.name "Your Name"
git config --global user.email you@example.com</programlisting>

    <para>It is time for our first commit</para>

    <programlisting>etckeeper commit "Changed etckeeper settings to disable auto commits"</programlisting>

    <para>To view the change log navigate to the <filename
    class="directory">/etc</filename> folder and run:</para>

    <programlisting>git log</programlisting>

    <para>You can learn more about git and etckeeper at the projects
    homepage.</para>

    <warning>
      <para>Remember to commit your changes after the each change you make or
      you will not be able to install packages because etckeeper will complain
      that there are uncommitted changes in the folder.</para>
    </warning>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="preparation.essentials">
    <title>Essential software</title>

    <para>First, we are going to install some software that we will use later
    in the manual.</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get install openssh-server nano dnsutils bsd-mailx telnet </programlisting>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         SSH server will allow us to connect remotely to the server. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         Nano is a text editor. More user friendly than vi. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         We will use wget to fetch stuff from the internet. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         dnsutils package will allow us to troubleshoot possible DNS problems on our system. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         Telnet and bsd-mailx will be used later for troubleshooting our setup. 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="preparation.static-ip">
    <title>Setting a static IP address</title>

    <para>If you didn't enter the IP address during the installation of the
    server, you probably got an address from the DHCP server. Since servers IP
    address should not be changed you will have to set a static IP address for
    your sever.</para>

    <para>Enter ifconfig at the prompt and copy the output somewhere so you
    have access to network information you got from a DHCP server.</para>

    <para>Open up <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> with nano and
    replace</para>

    <programlisting>auto eth0
iface eth0 inet dhcp</programlisting>

    <para>with</para>

    <programlisting>iface eth0 inet static
    address YOUR-IP
    netmask YOUR-NETMASK
    network YOUR-NETWORK
    broadcast YOUR-BROADCAST
    gateway YOUR-GATEWAY
    # dns-* options are implemented by the resolvconf package, if installed
    dns-nameservers YOUR-DNS-SERVERS-SEPARATED-BY-SPACE
    dns-search YOUR-DOMAIN</programlisting>

    <caution>
      <para>If you are using another interface for the connection replace
      <computeroutput>eth0</computeroutput> with the interface you are
      using.</para>
    </caution>

    <para>Reboot your server, check that your internet connection is working
    (try to ping google.com or some other host) and if everything is ok you
    can remove packages that provide DHCP from your system.</para>

    <programlisting>
apt-get --purge remove isc-dhcp-client isc-dhcp-common</programlisting>

    <para>Note that option –purge removes configuration files of the packages
    we are removing. If you do not use –purge they will be left on your
    system.</para>
  </section>

  <section version="5.0" xml:id="dns">
    <title>DNS settings</title>

    <note>
      <para>Mail server in this example is named <systemitem
      class="fqdomainname">atlantis.example.com</systemitem>. You can also
      name it <systemitem class="fqdomainname">mail.example.com</systemitem>
      if you like.</para>
    </note>

    <para>First, we need to check our hostname</para>

    <screen>atlantis:~# <command>hostname -f</command>
  atlantis.diabmon.com </screen>

    <para>If hostname did not return FQDN of your server edit
    <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>. You <filename>hosts</filename> file
    should look something like this, if not, change according to your IP
    address and server name.</para>

    <programlisting>127.0.0.1       localhost
  YOUR-IP-ADDRESS atlantis.example.com atlantis </programlisting>

    <para>Now check your <filename>/etc/hostname</filename> file it should
    contain your fully qualified domain name:</para>

    <programlisting>atlantis.example.com </programlisting>

    <para>Change the names to match your server name and reboot the server.
    Run <command>hostname -f</command> again and you should see <systemitem
    class="fqdomainname">atlantis.example.com</systemitem>.</para>

    <para>Now, we need to check that our DNS servers have an MX record for our
    <systemitem class="domainname">example.com</systemitem> domain. If you
    haven't done so already Install DNS utilities:</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get install dnsutils</programlisting>

    <para>We are going to use <command>host</command> command to check
    information about our domain:</para>

    <screen>atlantis:~# <command>host</command> example.com
  example.com has address YOUR-IP-ADDRESS
  example.com mail is handled by 0 mail.example.com. </screen>

    <para>We can see that the mail for our domain is handled by <systemitem
    class="fqdomainname">mail.example.com</systemitem>. Which server is
    supposed to handle mail for your domain is handled by the so called MX
    records in your domains zone file. Setting up DNS zone files is out of
    scope for this document.</para>

    <para>Now we must make sure that <systemitem
    class="fqdomainname">mail.example.com</systemitem> points to the same
    address as our server (<systemitem
    class="fqdomainname">atlantis.example.com</systemitem>).</para>

    <screen>atlantis:~# <command>nslookup</command> mail.example.com
  Server: YOUR-DNS-SERVER
  Address: YOUR-DNS-ADDRESS#53

  Non-authoritative answer:
  mail.example.com canonical name = atlantis.example.com.
  Name: example.com
  Address: YOUR-IP-ADDRESS </screen>

    <para>It would be also nice if your reverse DNS points to the same name
    (<systemitem
    class="fqdomainname">atlantis.example.com</systemitem>).</para>

    <screen>atlantis:~# <command>nslookup</command> YOUR-IP-ADDRESS
  Server: YOUR-DNS-SERVER
  Address: YOUR-DNS-SERVER#53

  Non-authoritative answer: 
  YOUR-IP-ADDRES-REVERSE.in-addr.arpa name = atlantis.example.com. </screen>

    <para>If they do not match you will probably have to ask your ISP to
    change this for you.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="preparation.ntp">
    <title>NTP - time synchronization</title>

    <para>Every server should have accurate time information, this is
    especially important for mail server. To make sure our servers time is
    always up to date we are going to install ntp package which enables our
    server to use NTP protocol for syncing your servers clock.</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get install ntp</programlisting>

    <para>If your data center or VPS provider offers an NTP service use their
    NTP server. Open up <filename>/etc/ntp.conf</filename> with nano and
    replace:</para>

    <programlisting>server 0.debian.pool.ntp.org iburst dynamic
server 1.debian.pool.ntp.org iburst dynamic
server 2.debian.pool.ntp.org iburst dynamic
server 3.debian.pool.ntp.org iburst dynamic</programlisting>

    <para>with</para>

    <programlisting>server ADDRESS-OF-NTP-SERVER-YOU-WANT-TO-USE</programlisting>

    <para>You should have at least two servers in the ntp.conf.</para>

    <para>After saving the changes you have to restart the NTP service by
    running</para>

    <programlisting>invoke-rc.d ntp restart</programlisting>

    <para>Note: invoke-rc.d is Debians shortcut to /etc/init.d/. You can run
    <computeroutput>/etc/init.d/ntp restart</computeroutput> as well.</para>

    <para>You can examine if the NTP server is working as expected if you run
    the ntpq -p command:</para>

    <screen>example:~# ntpq -p

    remote           refid      st t when poll reach   delay   offset  jitter
==============================================================================
zg1.ntp.CARNet. 161.53.1.2       2 u   58   64    3    7.157  106.619   4.158
zg2.ntp.CARNet. 161.53.1.2       2 u   57   64    3    7.677   25.934   4.792
morcic.RI.CARNe 161.53.1.2       2 u   58   64    3   11.796   26.527   7.751</screen>

    <para>After a while the reach column should have values greather that 0.
    Which means that the NTP servers we are pooling for time information are
    reachable.</para>

    <caution>
      <para>If your clock was way of from the current time NTP will not sync
      your servers time. In that case stop the NTP daemon. Set the time and
      date manually (or you can install and use the ntpdate utility) and run
      the NTP daemon again.</para>
    </caution>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="preparation.lamp">
    <title>Apache, MySQL and PHP</title>

    <para>If you plan to use Postfix Admin to manage your virtual users and
    domain, or provide webmail access to the email stored on the server you
    will have to install a web server.</para>

    <programlisting>apt-get install mysql-server mysql-client apache2 apache2-mpm-prefork apache2-utils ssl-cert \
                libapache2-mod-php5 php5 php5-common php5-curl php5-gd php-pear php5-imagick \
                php5-imap php5-mcrypt php5-mysql php5-pspell php5-sqlite php5-xmlrpc php5-xsl php5-intl</programlisting>

    <note>
      <para>This will also install Exim as the MTA. Uninstall it after you
      finish installing Postfix.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Default configuration of Apache sends server information in the
    response headers that we do not want to expose to everybody. To disable
    this open <filename>/etc/apache2/conf.d/security</filename> with nano and
    replace:</para>

    <programlisting>ServerTokens Full
ServerSignature On</programlisting>

    <para>with</para>

    <para><programlisting>ServerTokens Prod
ServerSignature Off</programlisting></para>

    <para>All application on my web server use UTF-8 as a default encoding so
    I also edit <filename>/etc/apache2/conf.d/charset</filename> and uncomment
    the <computeroutput>AddDefaultCharset UTF-8</computeroutput> directive
    which adds the UTF-8 as the default charset to the header for all files
    that Apache sends to clients.</para>

    <para>PHP also provides additional information in the response headers so
    we can turn off those as well.</para>

    <para>Open <filename>/etc/php5/apache2/php.ini</filename>. Change
    <computeroutput>expose_php = On</computeroutput> to
    <computeroutput>expose_php = Off</computeroutput> and set
    <varname>date.timezone= Europe/Zagreb</varname> (or whatever timezone you
    use). The link to a list of available time zones is located in the
    file.</para>

    <para>Enable mod_rewrite in Apache and restart Apache for the changes to
    take effe</para>

    <programlisting>a2enmod rewrite
invoke-rc.d apache2 restart</programlisting>
  </section>
</chapter>
